Guide to the Charles Bailey Reed scrapbooks and photographs, 1914-1924 and undated, bulk 1918-1919
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Charles Bailey Reed scrapbooks and photographs 1914-1924 and undated, bulk 1918-1919
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Reed, Charles Bailey.
1.6 linear feet Extent: Approx. 900 Items
Charles B. Reed was a radiologist in the U.S. Medical Reserve Corps during World War I; originally from Newburgh, Orange County, New York. Collection contains postcards, newspaper articles, printed matter, photographic prints and negatives, and ephemera collected by Charles Bailey Reed during his service with the U.S. Medical Reserve Corps in France during World War I, from about 1918 to 1919. Most of the items are mounted in several scrapbooks or were housed in loose groups within. Material relates very generally to World War I military medical practice. There are hundreds of black and white photographs, both loose and mounted, most taken by Reed from 1918-1919 around various cities in France, but others from a commercial source depicting earlier scenes from the British front in France, damaged buildings (including churches and cathedrals), battlefields, cemeteries, airfields, soldiers in camp and trenches, prisoners of war, downed planes, and dead enemy soldiers. Other topics and items of interest include Reed's images from Evacuation Hospital no. 1 in Sebastopol, newspaper coverage of the Armistice in November-December 1918, images from the Inter-Allied Games held in Paris in the summer of 1919, printed materials produced for American soldiers stationed in France, and images from a military base in N.Y. State, 1924. Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
RL.01074
Language: Material in English French German
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Charles Bailey Reed scrapbooks and photographs were received as a transfer by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 2011.
Collection Overview
The Charles Bailey Reed scrapbooks and photographs date from 1914-1924, and contain postcards, newspaper articles, printed matter, photographic prints and negatives, and ephemera collected by Charles Bailey Reed during his service with the U.S. Medical Reserve Corps in France during World War I, from about 1918-1919. Topics of interest include images from the front in France and the aftermath of the war, newspaper coverage of the Armistice in November-December 1918, images from various cities in France during the Armistice period, images from the Inter-Allied Games held in Paris in the summer of 1919, and printed materials produced for American soldiers stationed in France.
The majority of the collection, including undated material, stems from the end of the war and the immediate postwar period (1918-1919). Most of the material is arranged in two scrapbooks, but there is also loose material found at the end of the scrapbooks which has been rehoused, and there are also many loose photographic prints and negatives. The newspapers consist of the front page of the newspapers, with a few containing additional pages. Materials are arranged chronologically, with the exception of the photographs and postcards, which are arranged alphabetically by topic.
There are hundreds of black and white photographs, both loose and mounted in the scrapbooks, most deriving from Reed's service in France from 1918-1919. In a few cases they are accompanied by negatives. There are images probably taken by Reed or a fellow soldier, and a large group of what appear to be commercially-made images with captions in white lettering; some of the latter are dated 1914 and depict the British front in France (Alsace, Verdun), damaged buildings (including churches and cathedrals), battlefields, cemeteries, French and British soldiers in trenches and camps, dead soldiers (many of whom are German), and biplanes (including downed planes). Reed's photographs depict camps, soldiers' quarters, military vessels, ceremonies, tourist sites, damaged buildings, and a series of images from Evacuation Hospital No. 1 in Sebastopol, France. There is one image of what appears to be prisoners of war marching in a group. Other place names include Verdun, Alsace, Rheims, Paris, Marseilles, Cannes, and Avignon; there are some images from Alpine regions bordering Italy. One group of later photos is labeled "Watkins Glen, N.Y., 1918." Additionally, there are photos taken in 1924 of Pine Plains military camp in New York State, now part of Fort Drum.
Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Subject Headings
Reed, Charles Bailey; United States. Army. American Expeditionary Forces, 1917-1919; United States. Army. Medical Reserve Corps; Inter-Allied Games; Military bases -- New York (State); Military hospitals -- France; Soldiers -- France -- Pictorial works; World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1914-1918 -- France; World War, 1914-1918 -- Pictorial works; World War, 1914-1918 -- Armistices; World War, 1914-1918 -- Hospitals -- France; Europe -- World War, 1914-1918 -- Pictorial works; France -- World War, 1914-1918 -- Pictorial works; France -- World War, 1914-1918 -- History; Ephemera; Negatives; Newspapers; Black-and-white photographs; Postcards; Scrapbooks; History of Medicine Collections (Duke University)
Related Material
Charles Reed Correspondence (forms part of the Trent Manuscripts Collection)
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- World War I Scrapbooks Series, 1918-1921
  Two French-made, fabric-covered scrapbooks. Mounted items consist of hundreds of pieces related to the period shortly preceding the Armistice to 1921. There are photographic postcards, including many of wartime and Armistice events, color printed postcards, black and white photographs of battle sites and other wartime images, souvenir tickets and programmes, menus, hotel bills, and a few pieces of correspondence. One photographic postcard is the widely circulated image taken by a German soldier of Quentin Roosevelt's body posed lying in front of his downed plane in France, July 1918; he was the youngest son of Theodore Roosevelt. There were also many loose items found at the end of the scrapbooks that have been removed for improved housing and described separately in this inventory. A few loose items remain in their original locations in the scrapbooks.
  - Scrapbooks, 1918-1921 (Box 1-2)
- Photographic Prints Series, 1914-1924 and undated
  Black-and-white prints typically measure 2 1/4 x 3 1/8, or 2 3/4 x 4 1/2 inches; original envelopes with titles of contents are retained in the folders along with the prints. A few prints are captioned on the backs. Place names include Avignon, Cannes, Fontainebleu, Marseilles, Paris, Alsace, Rheims, and Verdun. The significance of "Kershaw," written on one envelope, has not been identified.
  - Allied Games, Eiffel Tower, Paris, undated (Box 3)
  - At camp, Pine Plains, 1924, July-Aug. [now Fort Drum, N.Y.] (Box 3)
  - Avignon, undated (Box 3)
  - Boat races, Paris, Versailles, undated, (negatives only) (Box 3)
  - British front, Lille, Zeebrugge, undated (Box 3)
  - Cannes, undated (Box 3)
  - Charles Bailey Reed, undated (Box 3)
  - Evacuation Hospital no. 1, Sebastapol, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Fontainebleu, undated (Box 3)
  - Kershaw, undated (Box 3)
    Includes views of a three-masted ship, a lake, Charles Reed on board a vessel, a city pier or quay, and an unidentified large mechanical shop. Envelope advertises a business in Central Valley, N.Y.
  - Marseilles, 1919, Feb. (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous--Alsace, Verdun, Paris, 1914-1919 (Box 3)
    Large group includes many small commercially-produced photographs of the front with captions, some dated 1914.
  - Monte Carlo, Italian border, undated (Box 3)
  - Neufchateau, undated (Box 3)
  - Paris and Versailles, undated (Box 3)
  - Rheims, undated (Box 3)
  - Watkins Glen, New York, 1918 (Box 3)
    Sites of interest include falls, the glen, lakes, hotels, and a downtown; includes shots of Reed and other men in uniform, and several views of an airfield in Beamsville, Canada, with biplanes (opened in early 1918).
  - X-ray repair shop, Paris, undated (Box 3)
  - Inter-Allied Games, set of published images produced by the U.S. Army Signal Corps, 1919 (Box 5)
- Ephemera Series, 1917-1919 and undated
  - (Removed from Scrapbook 1)
    - Letters, in German, from Berlin, 1918, April 21 and Aug. 5 (Box 4)
    - A.P.M. Paris registration coupons, 1918 (Box 4)
    - French currency, 1919 (Box 4)
    - French ration cards, 1919 (Box 4)
    - German Army postal service letter, blank, undated (Box 4)
    - German Army watch book, undated (Box 4)
    - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 4)
  - (Removed from Scrapbook 2)
    - Military orders, 1917 (Box 4)
    - Railway dining car receipt, 1918 (Box 4)
    - Newspaper clipping, 1919, May 23 (Box 4)
    - Automobile check, Inter-Allied Games, 1919 (Box 4)
    - Racing-club de France ticket, undated (Box 4)
- Newspapers Series, 1918-1919
  - (Removed from Scrapbook 1)
    - La Liberté, 1918, Nov. 11 (Box 5)
    - American Daily Mail, 1918, Nov. 17 (Box 5)
    - New York Herald, European edition, 1918, Nov. 20, 21, 29, 30; Dec. 3, 4, 15 (Box 5)
  - (Removed from Scrapbook 2)
    - New York Herald, European edition, 1919, June 24, July 11 (Box 5)
    - Excelsior, 1919, Aug. 8 (Box 5)
    - Unidentified newspaper, 1919, Oct. 19 (Box 5)
- Postcards Series, undated
  - (Removed from Scrapbook 1)
    - Cannes (Box 4)
    - Cornell University (Box 4)
    - Rouen (Box 4)
    - Verdun (Box 4)
- Printed Material Series, 1917-1919 and undated
  - (Removed from Scrapbook 1)
    - Instructions for Troops, 1917, Dec. 28 (Box 4)
    - B. van Vorst, France, Our Ally, 1918 (Box 4)
    - Seeing Nancy. A Guide for Americans with Map, 1918 (Box 4)
    - Amerika und der Weltkrieg, undated (Box 4)
    - Das Machinen-Gewehr 08. Lehrbuch für Unteroffiziere und Mannschaften, undated (Box 4)
    - Grand-Duchy of Luxemburg, undated (Box 4)
    - Pages of American Glory, undated (Box 4)
    - Paris, Monumental Métropolitain, undated (Box 4)
    - Roman Treves, Its History & Sights, undated (Box 4)
  - (Removed from Scrapbook 2)
    - Inter-Allied Games, Pershing Stadium, Joinville-le-Pont, Paris, 1919, July 4 (Box 4)
    - Le Sportif, Revue Hebdomadaire de Critique Sportive, 1919, July 19 (Box 4)
    - Who Can Tell? 88th Division Show, undated (Box 4)